Pablo Loza

About me

Electrical Engineer from the University of Chile with seven years of experience in the areas of Telecommunications and Construction (Renewable Energies). I have worked as head of engineering and as a specialist in TCP/IP and IPRAN 4G/5G networks, in charge of technical field personnel and document control. I managed to structure and operate the engineering area in an EPC of PV plants, delivering more than 9 successful projects of 3-9MWp and reducing design costs by 30%.

Both experiences with professional environments in English, besides working in different countries, I am looking for challenges that allow me to apply my experience in Energy and Telecommunications plus my adaptability to new environments, contributing to the growth of the organization.

Experience

Network Engineer, Claro, Chile - Telecommunication Operator

2022 - Now

- I managed and reviewed the quality of a nationwide technical study of the Claro Chile network, leading a team of 4 technicians and engineers and ensuring a 50% improvement to a total acceptance of the delivered documentation.
- Automated scripts for the implementation of Nokia, Huawei and ZTE routers for IPRAN. and implemented links for 4G/5G cellular network through Starlink, using VPNs on Fortinet firewalls.
- Network specialist for the massive transfer of corporate clients in neuralgic node closure. the engineering team in Fortinet technologies for the operation of VXLAN/VPN networks.
- I reviewed the database for the national project to provide high speed internet to schools for VTR, I also made the design of TX technologies to be implemented per school.
- I traced the network diagram for the migration of Claro's NOC to a new building, doing also part of the implementation.

Engineer Manager, GEOM, Santiago, Chile - ERNC Construction Company

2020 - 2021

- Created and led the Engineering and Procurement area for the design and construction of self-consumption photovoltaic projects and PMGD.
- In charge of the supervision and guidance of 5 technical specialists for the review of budgets, design and construction of more than 20MW making electrical, SCADA and civil drawings using AutoCAD.
- Developed unique technical solutions in the region such as wireless communication systems for Netbilling electrical control.
- Standardized processes and basic drawings for the design of Photovoltaic projects.
- Reviewed and provided support to solutions delivered by third party companies from different countries for PV implementations.
- Liaison with clients from different industries to provide technical and safety guarantees in the energy installations to be delivered.
- I conducted studies of new technologies in NCRE to implement them in future projects both in energy storage and SCADA.

Project Engineer Kubernet, Chile - TICs Consulting

2018 - 2019

- Part of the design and implementation team for the CGNAT firewall for the entire Claro Chile 4G network. Constant coordination with vendor teams in USA and China.
- Field recognition as engineer in charge of the IP backbone network for Claro Chile, making the technical documentation. Field technician and programmer for the installation of more than 20 sites for Claro Chile's IPRAN network, in addition to the design and implementation of various changes in the network topology.
- Field technician and programmer for the installation of more than 20 sites for Claro Chile's IPRAN network, in addition to the design and implementation of various changes in the network topology.

• Technical specialist in Fortinet firewalls, in medium and large companies I reviewed equipment in operation, created designs for improvements and implemented new equipment in active networks.

Education

University of Chile, Electric Engineer

2012 - 2018

- GPA/Chile: 3.3/6.2 (Verify)
- Coursework: Information and Communications Technologies; Energy and Power Systems; Digital Systems
- Research assistant: I worked on advanced AI studies applied to automotive and communications systems under the tutelage of PhD Jinsong Wu.

Technologies

Languages: Intermediate - Python, Experienced - MATLab, Familiar - Verilog, Familiar - C++.

Tecnologías: Network routing IP (Cisco, Nokia, ZTE, Huawei), SD-WAN, MSOffice, Firewall, PVcase, AutoCAD.

Certified: Network Security Expert - Level IV

Idiomas

Spanish: Nativo.

English: Advanced professional, WT program with 6 months working in the U.S.

Portuguese: Intermediate, six months living in Brazil.

Mandarin Chinese: Basic, 1st course approved at the Confucius Institute - PUC.

References

Vicente Gumucio

- GEOM Renewable Energies / CTO
- +56-9-7806-6198; vgumucio@geom.cl

Domingo Becerra

- Kubernet CTO Consultant Claro
- +56-9-5401-6134; domingo.becerra@kubernet.cl

PhD Jinsong Wu

- PhD Associate Professor, Department of Electrical Engineering, Universidad de Chile.
- +56-2-2978-4761; jinsongwu@ing.uchile.cl